<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Travel | Jason Morrison]]></title>
  <link href="http://jayunit.net/blog/categories/travel/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jayunit.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-02T22:53:57-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://jayunit.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jason Morrison]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Year of Travel]]></title>
    <link href="http://jayunit.net/2012/12/31/a-year-of-travel/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-31T09:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jayunit.net/2012/12/31/a-year-of-travel</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On December 4, Lindsay and I returned to the US after a year of <a href="/2011/11/11/hitting-the-road/">traveling
abroad</a>.  Lindsay diligently blogged our
experiences and her photos at <a href="http://cadeparade.com">cadeparade.com</a>.</p>

<p>We have spent December visiting family and friends.  On December 31, we
fly to San Francisco to start the next chapter of our lives.</p>

<h2>It&rsquo;s adventure time all over again</h2>

<p>Time to sift through apartments and carefully consider our work, to reacquaint
ourselves with first world amenities and first world problems.  To reunite with
family and friends, to fondly shuffle through our notes and photos, and to
reflect on our travel experiences and put them into context.</p>

<p>Also, to eat fajitas and burritos en masse, because let me tell you: Mexican
and Tex-Mex food outside the Americas just is not the same.</p>

<h2>The first half in photos</h2>

<p><em>All photos are by <a href="http://cadeparade">Lindsay Cade</a>, and are from the first
half of the year.</em></p>

<p>During the first six months of December 2011 through May 2012, we traveled in
India, Thailand, Laos, Vietname, Cambodia, and Burma (Myanmar).</p>

<p>We traveled to places beautiful and remote:</p>

<p><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8453/7936991528_886ea7ae7c_b.jpg" alt="" />
<img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8448/7936993184_be9e720c99_c.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Ate incredible foods:</p>

<p><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7257/7768788654_e7b744e282_b.jpg" alt="" />
<img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7216/7215266698_43e7409e59_b.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>And some not-so-incredible ones:</p>

<p><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7199/6927499007_1732d60f76_b.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>We enjoyed amazing sunsets:</p>

<p><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7105/6981860512_18047acd9d_b.jpg" alt="" />
<img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5032/7078843175_0eb29b087c_c.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>We ventured across deserts:</p>

<p><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7203/6891841828_dc95fc8352_c.jpg" alt="" />
<img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7254/7031251719_51598ea65d_c.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>into backwaters:</p>

<p><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7208/6847221555_1d21839826_b.jpg" alt="" />
<img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7077/7050364455_1d44c6d27b_b.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>through rivers and valleys:</p>

<p><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8421/7741985230_becb4193c3_b.jpg" alt="" />
<img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7022/6784074323_212570b388_b.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>We marvelled at constructions old and new:</p>

<p><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7142/6640567045_49dc8ddc58_b.jpg" alt="" />
<img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7032/6634037347_a7c9c91e4c_b.jpg" alt="" />
<img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7071/7006734540_c688343639_b.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>During the second six months of June through November, we traveled in the Czech
Republic, Italy, Turkey, Germany, France, England, Thailand (again! we are
quite fond of it), South Korea, Malaysia, and Hong Kong.  We ended the trip
where we began, returning to India for a month.</p>

<p>I cannot recommend this experience highly enough.  My sense of perspective and
patience have been changed at a fundamental level.  At the same time, I&rsquo;m very
much ready for this return to the US, to be with friends and to focus on my
career, to do good in this world of which I&rsquo;ve now seen a tiny slice more.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hitting the Road!]]></title>
    <link href="http://jayunit.net/2011/11/11/hitting-the-road/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-11T09:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jayunit.net/2011/11/11/hitting-the-road</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On November 28, my wife Lindsay and I are flying to India.  We have
no return tickets, and little plan.  I&rsquo;m leaving a <a href="http://thoughtbot.com">great job</a>;
&ldquo;professional ennui&rdquo; is the furthest thing from my motivations.  What&rsquo;s going on?!</p>

<p><img src="/images/uploads/adventure-time.png" alt="Adventure Time!" /></p>

<h2>It&rsquo;s adventure time!</h2>

<p>If there&rsquo;s one common lesson I could distill from my collegiate and
professional engagements, it would be the value of diverse experience, and the
difficulty of <em>planning</em> to build that experience.  Sometimes you just gotta
jump in learning&rsquo;s way.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re young, not tied down, and have seen like 0.0001% of the world.  So,
earlier this year, after getting engaged, we decided: let&rsquo;s hit the road!  Our
plans are loose.  As of now, we:</p>

<ul>
<li>Have 1-way tickets to Delhi and 5-year visas to India.  Many countries in
Asia have VOA (visa on arrival) for US citizens.</li>
<li>Got our arms jabbed (immunizations).</li>
<li>Are brandishing a fat sack of doxy and a veritable menagerie of antibiotics.</li>
<li>Booked two days booked at a hotel to buffer our jetlag.</li>
<li>Asked a friend-of-a-friend to find a short-term lease in Delhi.</li>
<li>Are super frigging pumped.  I mean, come on!</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;ll miss the crap out of my friends here in the US.  We&rsquo;re flying around a bit
to visit folks before heading overseas &ndash; San Fran tomorrow through Wednesday,
then Buffalo, then Houston for Thanksgiving.</p>

<p>Then, on November 28, IAH-ORD-DEL.</p>

<h2>Closing thoughts</h2>

<blockquote><p>Journeys are the midwives of thought. Few places are more conducive to internal
conversations than a moving plane, ship or train. There is an almost quaint
correlation between what is in front of our eyes and the thoughts we are able
to have in our heads: large thoughts at times requiring large views, new
thoughts new places. Introspective reflections which are liable to stall are
helped along by the flow of the landscape. The mind may be reluctant to think
properly when thinking is all it is supposed to do.</p>

<p>If we find poetry in the service station and motel, if we are drawn to the
airport or train carriage, it is perhaps because, in spite of their
architectural compromises and discomforts, in spite of their garish colours and
harsh lighting, we implicitly feel that these isolated places offer us a
material setting for an alternative to the selfish ease, the habits and
confinement of the ordinary, rooted world.</p></blockquote>

<p>― Alain de Botton, The Art of Travel</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
